<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbookxi.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>Things We Lost in the Fire</title>
        <author>
            <personname><firstname>Geert</firstname><surname>Bormans</surname></personname>
        </author>
        <author>
            <personname><firstname>Ari</firstname><surname>Nordström</surname></personname>
        </author>
    </info>
    <section xml:id="stakeholders-view">
        <title>Memories</title>
        <para>Bitching about our projects, we came to realise that many of our projects follow a
            pattern. This pattern can be illustrated through the diagram below.</para>
        <para>If we reduce the number of stakeholders in a project to three, there seems always to
            be someone (or a team) in power, a team doing the technical work, and a consultant
            either providing advice or helping development.</para>
        <para>All three stakeholders have a certain view on the project: where the resources should
            go, what technology or approach should be used, and what the best route to success
            should be. Obviously the project's succes would depend on the space where views
            meet.</para>
        <para>However we cme to the conclusion that this zone of succes, for various undefined
            reasons, often is a <quote>hidden zone</quote> or even a <quote>forbidden
            zone</quote>.</para>
        <figure>
            <title>That Basic Venn Diagram</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="img/Hidden-zone.jpg"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>If you're one of us - a grumpy old man, basically<footnote>
                <para>No harm in being a grumpy old woman here.</para>
            </footnote>, with some years of angled brackets under your belt - you will recognise
            this diagram, nodding and — perhaps — bitterly thinking back in time. You will have had
            many experiences relating directly to this simple diagram. Memories.</para>
        <para>This is a paper about those memories. We'll tell you about some of
                <emphasis>our</emphasis> memories, reliving the key points, bitching about what we
            went through while thinking — hoping, even — that you'll be nodding right along with
            us.</para>
    </section>

</article>
