<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbookxi.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
        xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>Things We Lost in the Fire</title>
        <author>
            <personname><firstname>Geert</firstname><surname>Bormans</surname></personname>
        </author>
        <author>
            <personname><firstname>Ari</firstname><surname>Nordström</surname></personname>
        </author>
        <abstract>
            <para>This is about all those markup consulting projects where you realise that
                something isn't quite as it should be. Early on, your internal alarm bells are set
                off by a technology choice, legacy systems or processes, or maybe internal
                conflicts, and you realise there are some hard decisions to make. Yes, you have
                bills to pay but is this one of those projects you should stay away from... or have
                stayed away from in the first place?</para>
            <para>For example, what if you realise that your project was never meant to succeed?
                What if a legacy system stands in the way of your every deliverable but is regarded
                as untouchable? And what if you've been brought in to solve pressing and immediate
                problems but office politics, legacy systems, fundamental misconceptions or all of
                the above stand in your way? What if the team's skill set would be a trigger to
                obstruction and sabotage? What if people were losing their jobs if you were
                successful? Or maybe it's simply a disruptive atmosphere and more than anything it's
                all about breaking through that.</para>
            <para>We take a hard look at past projects and try to analyse what went wrong and why,
                and what we learned from them. Perhaps we can impart some degree of objectivity on a
                novice in the field, or at least have him or her think again. If there is success -
                flipping adversity into success - we’ll be more than happy to claim credit.</para>
            <para>While the stories are unlikely to be impartially presented, the names of the
                innocent (and not-so innocent) will be protected. We will instead focus on
                distilling the essence of each story and consider patterns and common denominators
                so we can learn from them. The listener will hopefully learn from our mistakes while
                nodding in recognition - we do not claim uniqueness;
                <?oxy_comment_start author="C-Moria" timestamp="20200202T195134+0100" comment="I like the fact that the extended abstract we sent in is used here to introduce the paper. I am however not certain about this final paragraph. The &quot;we hpe to entertain&quot; is a suggestion fro wahtw e had in mind for the presentation. Only one paragraph later we hint again to &quot;a few laughs&quot; Maybe that is a bit too much hinting to being funny"?>if
                all else fails, we hope to entertain.<?oxy_comment_end?></para>
        </abstract>
    </info>
    <section>
        <title>We Call Ourselves Grumpy Old Men</title>
        <para>Let us introduce ourselves. We're a pair of somewhat aged markup
            geeks<?oxy_comment_start author="C-Moria" timestamp="20200202T195202+0100" comment="Break this sentence here maybe"?>,
            <?oxy_comment_end?>having worked in the field for some 50 years combined, a lot of which
            was spent bitching about what had already been. This is not the paper that will reveal
            all. However, it is the paper that will discuss some of the implications of those 50
            years.</para>
        <para>Or at least have a few laughs while reminiscing.</para>
        <section xml:id="stakeholders-view">
            <title><?oxy_comment_start author="C-Moria" timestamp="20200202T195401+0100" comment="I added a section to have a single Xinclude identifier. In its context, I think the content of this section can be pulled in the main section... would be one less title (and maybe a better flow
"?>Memories<?oxy_comment_end?></title>
            <para>Bitching about our projects, we came to realise that many of our projects follow a
                pattern. This pattern can be illustrated through the diagram below.</para>
            <para>If we would reduce the number of stakeholders in a project to three, there seems
                always to be someone (or a team) in power, a team doing the technical work, and a
                consultant either providing advice or assisting development.</para>
            <para>All three stakeholders have a certain view on the project: where the resources
                should go, what technology or approach should be used, and what the best route to
                success would be. Obviously the project's succes would depend on the space where all
                views meet.</para>
            <para>However we came to the conclusion that this zone of succes, for various undefined
                reasons, often is a <quote>hidden zone</quote> or even a <quote>forbidden
                    zone</quote>.</para>
            <figure>
                <title>That Basic Venn Diagram</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="img/Hidden-zone.jpg"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>If you're one of us - a grumpy old man, basically<footnote>
                    <para>No harm in being a grumpy old woman here.</para>
                </footnote>, with some years of angled brackets under your belt - you will recognise
                this diagram, nodding and — perhaps — bitterly thinking back in time. You will have
                had many experiences relating directly to this simple diagram. Memories.</para>
            <para>This is a paper about those memories. We'll tell you about some of
                    <emphasis>our</emphasis> memories, reliving the key points, bitching about what
                we went through while thinking — hoping, even — that you'll be nodding right along
                with us.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    
    <section>
        <title>Matches</title>
        <!--<title><?oxy_comment_start author="C-Moria" timestamp="20200202T200151+0100" comment="I think I understand what you mean. I think we can drop the &quot;Religion&quot; level titles. Grouping could be implicit... I agree they could go

What if we did this:
Paper title: &quot;Things we lost in the fire&quot;
section1 &quot;We call ourselves Grumpy Old Men&quot;
here goes introduction
section 2 &quot;Things that ignited the sparks&quot;
here go all the stories with subsection titles
section 3 &quot;Things we found in the ashes&quot;
here goes teh conclusion"?>Religion<?oxy_comment_end?></title>-->
        <section>
            <title><?oxy_comment_start author="C-Moria" timestamp="20200202T200215+0100" comment="however keeping these divisions"?>Programming<?oxy_comment_end?>
                Languages as Religion</title>
            <para dir="ltr">Being too religious about a programming language or a vocabulary does
                not always help a project.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">Some years ago I held a workshop after the audit of an XML
                transformation code base. I was invited to do so because the customer found out that
                very small functional changes to the existing proprietary transformer really took
                developers a lot of time to develop and testing always revealed that a small fix at
                one point raised another issue elsewhere.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">It was obvious they were using the wrong technology for the job at
                hand.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">I managed to convince the managers in the workshop that a different
                technology (XSLT to no surprise) would pay off quickly, as it would be a much better
                fit to the job. After a coffee break we would discuss migration plans,
                training...</para>
            <para dir="ltr">None of the developers present realised I understood the local language,
                so near the coffee machine I overheard an agitated discussion about the techology.
                One of the developers mentioned firmly that XSLT would only be used "<quote>over his
                    dead body</quote>"</para>
            <para dir="ltr">I was assured by the manager that they would handle the situation
                without much problems and we planned migration, training, contracts.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">After my flight back home, there was a message on my voicemail thanking
                me for the audit and workshop. The project however was cancelled early because of
                developer protest.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>The Strict
                <?oxy_comment_start author="C-Moria" timestamp="20200202T201853+0100" comment="We don&apos;t put dates at most stories. This story would be enforced if you could tigh this to post 2015. A strict DTD would be less a really bad plan in 2000 then it was last year. Don&apos;t say it was 2019. Because people will relate this to your paper presented twice in this community... just to not make an obvious fool from Karnov
"?>DTD<?oxy_comment_end?></title>
            <para dir="ltr">I wrote a set of DTDs and a bunch of transformation pipelines for a
                client that was merging their content with another company’s (as in actually merging
                two sets of documents with the same text but with differing tagging). Among the DTDs
                was an exchange DTD, an intermediate format when converting from one format to
                another, and a somewhat more strict DTD for authoring the merged content. The two
                DTDs were related, of course; the exchange format was the intermediate format used
                when converting external documents from whatever source they used to the new
                authoring DTD.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">In my mind, the big job was to move from the external source to the
                exchange format. Moving from the exchange format to the authoring format was mostly
                about tidying things up. Typically, the first pipeline, from the source to exchange,
                would be in the range of 80 or so XSLT steps while the second pipeline, from
                exchange to authoring, was 18 steps. The authoring format would still have various
                optional structures, though, and #IMPLIED attributes, as the merge resulted in
                inevitable compromises. My plan was to add a Schematron to do some additional
                validation and tightening-up, based on the authoring format.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">But when some of the other company’s devs heard about my plans, they
                said “we MUST do a stricter DTD to aid the authors!” Nonplussed, I repeated the bits
                about additional validation using a Schematron. Maybe they missed that part.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">“No, we MUST have a strict DTD!”</para>
            <para dir="ltr">This was getting weird. I explained that there was no way to do that
                strict DTD - things would have to remain optional and #IMPLIED, or quite a few
                documents wouldn’t be valid. I asked what they had against the DTD+SCH combo. We’re
                talking about well-known and well-supported standards. There were no actual answers
                at first, only the insistence of a strict DTD, “because authors have a hard time
                knowing what to do if the DTD doesn’t properly guide them.”</para>
            <para dir="ltr">I went through what’s normally my sales pitch about the usefulness and
                adaptability of Schematron rules, and how they can help authors in ways DTDs cannot.
                And thinking that I shouldn’t have to be doing this.
                T<?oxy_comment_start author="C-Moria" timestamp="20200202T202155+0100" comment="maybe tone down the frustration ;-)... it is obvious this one is recent ;-)
"?>hey
                were devs, ferchrissakes. But they ins<?oxy_comment_end?>isted, stating that they
                knew what Schematrons were and they did think they were useful, but... and they got
                their boss (who wouldn’t know a Schematron even if one bit him) to back them
                up.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">Much later, I had a one-on-one with one of the devs and the conversation
                drifted to Schematrons. And after some discussion, he finally said “Schematron is a
                Java library, right?”</para>
            <para dir="ltr">This is about pride and firmly set beliefs. And it’s also about devs
                with too much power.</para>
        </section>
    
    
        <!--<title>Misconceptions</title>-->
        <section>
            <title>Page by Page</title>
            <para dir="ltr">I was tasked with collecting requirements from a number of companies
                owned by the same global monster in order to design a single system and associated
                schemas and processes for handling the documentation and publishing needs of all
                those companies.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">This one company I talked to needed their manuals published in 27
                languages (EU, mostly, as you might guess) but their output was handled in, shall we
                say, a doubtful manner. </para>
            <para dir="ltr">Basically, they had one MS Word file per manual page. A 70-page manual
                would thus consist of 70 files. They then made sure that the translations of one
                page - or file - would fit into that same page, including images and
                everything.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">All 27 languages would thus have the same number of pages, which they
                thought was great and really cost-saving because they’d then be able to use the same
                ToCs and indexes regardless of language.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">And so they thought the natural progression from this state would be to
                do those files in XML instead, because writing and translating saves a lot of money.
                Right??</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>The Strict DTD, Part 2</title>
            <para>The whole Strict DTD debacle was as much about misconceptions as it was about
                religion, of course. The religion was in the magic of DTDs while the misconceptions
                were about Schematrons. But the really worrying bits were all about them
                    <emphasis>not knowing what Schematrons do but pretending they
                did.</emphasis></para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>We've Always Done This</title>
            <para dir="ltr">Recently I developed (yet another) MS Word transformer to XML. Yes,
                customers do use MS Word for XML authoring.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">I was called in because a first attempt had failed over the past few
                years.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">This story is about legal publishing. Some acts have books, chapters and
                sections, others just have chapters, and yet others have deeper nesting. The
                information model caters for all of that.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">The contractor had told the publisher that it was impossible to
                differentiate between a chapter in one document or another if chapters would not
                always be styled reliably on the same level. For example, the project could only be
                successful if chapters were always styled as <code>heading3</code> and sections as
                    <code>heading4</code>. So the publisher started restyling all their content to
                be in line with the contractors requirements... and gave up on that effort after
                some 1,000 pages out of 200,000.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>We've Always Done This, Part 2</title>
            <para dir="ltr">I inherited the stylesheet development work of an old DITA OT project in
                the automotive industry for print and HTML. Challenging, quite a few car types, over
                20 languages including Hebrew and Arab.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">For some years by the time I joined, the information architect had
                defined every suggestion from the car manufacturer about the printed pages into
                separate tasks for stylesheet development. The reviewers of those printed manuals
                all had different ideas, sometimes conflicting, and the response of the information
                architect had always been to allow for exceptions to be fixed in the
                stylesheets.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">It had never occurred to them to fix anything in the actual DITA
                content, except to add another output class every once in a while.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">There was a continuous pressure to publish, one car model after another,
                one language after another, each one leading to incremental changes to the
                stylesheets, causing massive delays in delivering the printed manuals. The DITA OT
                developer had indicated he no longer had the time to handle all the work coming
                in.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">So I was hired for some smaller development tasks and inherited a code
                base that had more <code>xsl:if</code> and <code>xsl:when</code> clauses then it had
                templates. I slowly started changing the mentality from fix-in-stylesheets (one part
                time developer) to fix-in-content (5 full time editors) but never managed to change
                course in time.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">Eventually my contractor lost his contract because of the delays.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">The same contractor then got the brilliant idea to start using their
                expertise and DITA for a legal content publishing project. I politely passed on that
                one.</para>
        </section>
    
    
        <!--<title>Teams</title>-->
        <section>
            <title>90-minute Standups</title>
            <para dir="ltr">In the early days of using agile development methods, I worked half time
                for a somewhat smaller integrator. A single big project consumed most of the
                company's resources and also charged some of the work out to consultants such as
                myself.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">In order to glue all of teams efforts together we had a daily standup
                meeting with about 45 people. The daily standup took an hour, sometimes up to 90
                minutes. Working only halftime in the project, I was still attending the standup
                every day. Well, I got dismissed from the standup after I started mentioning the
                daily meeting explicitly in my timesheets.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">In the end, the end-customer cancelled the project for budgetary
                reasons.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>The Build Is Green</title>
            <para dir="ltr">Speaking of agile development, in a project I once worked in there were
                some trained <quote>scrum masters</quote> doing the Java development part of the
                work. They were extremely keen on using all the techniques they learned in the
                project: pair programming but mainly Test Driven Development.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">After setting up a test environment and a big screen, their only focus
                to the project became <quote>making the build green</quote>.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">At some point we had a couple of rough days in the project, and "the
                build" had been red for days. Suddenly the scrum masters started singing <quote>the
                    build is green, the build is green</quote> and prepared to leave for the
                evening. Well it had never been as bad as on that particular point. Everything broke
                apart, no results to be found anywhere.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">Pointing that out the response was: <quote>You can not spoil the fun,
                    the build is green</quote>.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">They left the office with a suggestion... if there is something you
                don't like, you will have to write a test for that.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Make It Better</title>
            <para dir="ltr">We do often get so focused on the technical aspects of a task that we
                forget about the legacy or the team.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">In a very recent gig the task was very clear: work through the codebase
                and make it better. It needs to be more robust and should run faster. Reaching the
                set goals would not be extremely difficult. The existing code was already above
                average, and improving on some of the techniques used would already make enough of a
                difference. However, it was hard to get all the teams to accept the things I was
                doing until a sprint evaluation revealed that people disliked the black-box approach
                I took.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">The development team came up with a plan to have a weekly meeting to
                discuss the changes made so far and the reasons for making the change. That
                communicative approach made a huge difference for the atmosphere and
                cooperation.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">It is all so obvious after the facts, but t taught me to have even more
                attention for the different sensitivities in a team.</para>
        </section>
    
    
        <!--<title>Office Politics</title>-->
        <section>
            <title>An XSD for Appearances</title>
            <para dir="ltr">I was tasked with designing an XSD for a client. The XSD was supposedly
                for describing messages in a system. The work was to be done on site and my contract
                was for six weeks. Oh, and this was in around 2005, before the advent of the
                smartphone, mobile internet, etc.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">There was no computer ready for me when I arrived. That is, the hardware
                was there but the software wasn’t. It was “on order” from the IT department. I
                didn’t have much interaction with the other devs, just specs from an initial
                implementation proposal and some mostly irrelevant background information. I also
                didn’t have much contact with the other devs; they were busy coding their thing
                based on the implementation proposal, plus their own ideas (which I found out
                later). The only guy I really talked to was the project manager, mostly because he
                was a friend.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">Luckily, I had my own personal laptop. No internet connection since this
                was on-site and foreign computers were a no-no, so no email, but I had my own
                software for the XML stuff, plus all those implementation proposal specs (which I
                pretty much followed to the letter).</para>
            <para dir="ltr">I delivered an XSD that did exactly what it was supposed to on time
                during week #6, on a floppy disk since I had no means to deliver without an internet
                connection.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">On the Friday of week #6, I had lunch with the project manager. He said
                “we’re not going to use your XSD.” And the computer I was appointed never got its
                software.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">I later realised that the waterfall, up-front approach was probably not
                what the devs or the company wanted and their solution never included an XSD. It
                was, however, described in the proposal, and so it was preordained which meant that
                it had to be included in the project. Yes, that’s me. But <emphasis role="italic">my
                    XSD was never meant to be included in the solution</emphasis>.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">So this one is about a task destined, even designed, to fail, a feature
                meant to be excluded from the finished product. I suppose it’s about the downsides
                of waterfall methodologies, too, where you have to include something because it was
                in the IP. And it’s about office politics, the nasty variety where they exclude
                people from their meetings based on, well, a feature that was never meant to be
                there.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">We could add this as “office politics” but this sort of means that
                everything is about office politics.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Strict DTD, Part 3</title>
            <para>Remember that Strict DTD? It was meant to do both the work of a DTD and what you'd
                normally entrust Schematrons and style guides with, but the project was also very
                much about office politics. The procedure went something like this:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Them: <quote>We want our strict DTD!</quote></para>
                    <para>Us: <quote>It will make thousands of documents invalid. We can't do it.
                            Use a bloody Schematron instead!</quote></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Them: <quote>We also want to use language X rather than
                        English!</quote></para>
                    <para>Us: <quote>How's that going to work with all of our non-X
                            developers?</quote></para>
                    <para>Them: <quote>We'll write instructions!</quote></para>
                    <para>Us: <quote>Sorry, we might as well do the DTD in Klingon!<footnote>
                                <para>Which is what I did, for a select number of attributes. It
                                    took them about two months or so to spot it.</para>
                            </footnote></quote></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Them: </para>
                    <para>(Office politics happens.)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Us: </para>
                    <para><quote>Let's do a black-box solution that translates between the Strict
                            DTD (for authoring) and the sensible DTD/Schematron combo that doesn't
                            wreck anything!</quote> (Suggested and implemented by my team
                        leader.)</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>As I write this, they have an actual black box thing that translates XML between
                the DB storage format and the authoring format. And the two are
                    <emphasis>not</emphasis> fully compatible so there are a lot of problems each
                way and more being discovered every day.</para>
        </section>
    
    
        <!--<title>Software</title>-->
        <section>
            <title>Open Source as Policy</title>
            <para dir="ltr">Around 20 years ago, a publisher invited me to look into the publication
                process of one of their somewhat more intensive publications.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">There was a team of about 10 developers. This means the department had
                10 computers. One of the developers had designed a system that would make the
                publication, occupying all the computers in the department full time for three
                days.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">Incidentally, the solution required Sablotron, Perl and a lot of network
                communication.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">That implied they had to wait for a long weekend to publish. If
                something failed during the process, they'd have to wait for the next long weekend.
                The publication was often delayed by several months because of that.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">I looked into this and could prove that the entire process could be done
                in just a few hours on a single machine. However, this required the use of a
                reasonably priced licensed software.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">The manager refused the proposal because it failed against their open
                source software-only policy... and the existing solution did work, didn't it? They
                continued to use the existing approach for a couple more years.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Old Software</title>
            <para dir="ltr">Speaking of licensed software, I had to work around missing
                functionality doing XSLT development in the DITA Open Toolkit a number of times,
                simply because it came bundled with a 10 year-old XSLT2.0 processor. That seemed to
                be the only option to use a <code>node-set()</code> extension function without
                paying a license cost.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">Effectively, I had to spend multiple hours to work around a license cost
                equalling about one of those hours. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Subscription Services</title>
            <para dir="ltr">I am running a subscription service providing some transformed data in
                specific formats to subscribers. However I am getting the actual information for
                this service from crawling databases via a web interface. This is all nicely covered
                by a ten year old contract with the information provider.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">But then, one day the information provider was purchased by an
                international consortium and the new owners simply blocked my server's IP address.
                Information could now only be obtained through the API they had developed, but they
                no longer had room for another partner.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">It took me weeks and a good lawyer to force myself into a partner
                agreement. Then it took me weeks to replace the crawler with a service that
                communicated with the API.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">During that period I lost half of the subscribers to a service that was
                supposed to update at least weekly.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>You Can Choose Any Software You Want</title>
            <para dir="ltr">A well-known global automotive manufacturer needed to XML-ify their
                aftermarket documentation using a system they wanted us to design and build (at the
                time they mostly used PageMaker for their aftermarket docs). I was first out, to
                analyse requirements, write DTDs, and recommend ways to do the system so it would
                support everything in a really, really cool way.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">My analysis of the existing documents (glovebox manuals, accessory
                catalogues, warranty booklets, etc) suggested a lot of savings to be made by
                modularising the information, aided by some light profiling (different engines,
                gearboxes, etc), linking, and general standardisation of processing. I wrote a set
                of DTDs using all the then-modern technologies such as extended XLink<footnote>
                    <para>Xinclude wasn’t really a thing at that point.</para>
                </footnote> and set up a list of cool things we could do with the system.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">This is when they came back with a bunch of requirements:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem dir="ltr">
                    <para dir="ltr">You can choose any editor you want but it has to be Arbortext
                        Epic</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem dir="ltr">
                    <para dir="ltr">You can choose any underlying DB you want but it all needs to be
                        based on Documentum.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem dir="ltr">
                    <para dir="ltr">You really should use that new formatting engine Arbortext
                        provides (but please use any standards you want). Was it called E3?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem dir="ltr">
                    <para dir="ltr">Oh, and we need you to move all the old SGML stuff we have for
                        service info, parts DB (COBOL!), and the like to the new system as well.
                        Which means going from SGML to XML.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para dir="ltr">Let’s see. No extended XLink (because of no way to properly handle
                out-of-line lookups in the editor OR the DB). No inline <code>CDATA</code>-based
                links either (because Arbortext and FOSIs at the time did not do them).</para>
            <para dir="ltr">Which meant generating <code>ID/IDREF</code> pairs in a really mad
                process whenever handling the information, plus a LOT of other compromises.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">They also decided the driver’s manuals couldn't be done in XML because
                there would be compromises in the layout and the manuals need to look pretty. Never
                mind that we go to 42 languages and by not using XML we add a 70% cost to every
                single manual produced. PageMaker it is.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">And no, let’s not do the accessory catalogues in XML either, for similar
                reasons.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">Documentum was added a DMS layer that required horrible processing
                attributes on many elements (this is how we found out that Arbortext’s parser at the
                time included a hard 8,000-character attribute length limit). The first login in
                test took about 30 minutes. In the words of the software architect: <quote>This
                    could have been a really fast system without Documentum.</quote> I said
                something in a similar vein about Arbortext, and the guy who did most of the FOSIs
                cursed about E3.</para>
            <para>The system ended up costing about ten or fifteen times the budget, required a LOT
                of bug fixing (the cost of which wasn't part of the inflated budget), but it's
                supposedly still in use.</para>
        </section>
    
    
        <!--<title>Legacy</title>-->
        <section>
            <title>Those Were the Days</title>
            <para dir="ltr">I was tasked with writing an XSD for a company that wanted to move away
                from this ancient COBOL monster with heavily typed data ensuring that they’d never
                go past a couple of Megabytes, created in a time when every byte cost a
                fortune.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">Yet, it quickly became apparent that they chose XSDs because the data
                described by them can be typed… just like before. In the end, I delivered a schema
                that rather faithfully reproduced that old CBOL monster but with no additional
                value.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">This is not about a legacy system as much as it is about a legacy
                mindset. I could have avoided the pain simply by asking <quote>what do you want to
                    achieve with your new XSD?</quote>”</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Latin 1 and Entitites</title>
            <para dir="ltr">Publisher X stores all of their documents - hundreds of thousands of
                them - in an old, heavily customised Oracle DB. They’ve built a document management
                layer on top of the thing but they don’t really have proper versioning on either
                documents or the DTDs that govern them. They still run OmniMark scripts to do
                validation, some light processing and the like.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">Oh, and it’s all in Latin 1, with about 250 or so general entities. This
                includes the Omnimark scripts.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">Long before I first knew the company, they’ve been wanting to move to
                UTF-8 but the management and various project decisions have consistently held them
                back. They’ve bought companies and merged entire content libraries with their own,
                and it’s all been converted to… Latin 1. On an office whiteboard, there is a counter
                for the number of days since the last encoding-related error that never wanders far
                from “1”; in other words, there are issues almost daily, ranging from web pages that
                refuse to format to documents that refuse to load to that ancient Oracle DB.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">Yet, the company handles this technical debt mostly by ignoring it.
                They’ve built new presentation systems and increased their print offering, and now
                they’re about to add a MarkLogic DB on the side. MarkLogic will mirror Oracle and
                will be used for analysis to begin with; in time, it might replace the Oracle
                monster.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">One assumes that they’ll somehow incorporate Latin 1 and DTDs in it,
                though, since while they’re always saying that they MUST move to Unicode and UTF-8,
                everything else always comes first.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    
    
    <section>
        <title>Opposing Views</title>
        <section>
            <title>Sometimes SGML Is What You Want</title>
            <para dir="ltr">I was part of a consulting effort to deliver a new system to an
                aerospace company and among the first in to take a long hard look at their current
                information set, most of which was early S1000D SGML. This was close to 20 years
                ago.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">After careful consideration, I realised that them using SGML was just
                fine; no need to author in XML, no need to write an XML DTD or use the XML version
                of the standard (S1000D back then did not yet have a proper XML DTD or schema, or
                proper support for it) and migrate the content. All we needed was a modern approach
                to authoring, managing, and storing the SGML, and a bunch of conversions to XML and
                other formats <emphasis role="italic">when publishing</emphasis>. Their suppliers
                all used SGML, and they delivered to companies and organisations that all used SGML.
                No need to change any of this; it would be costly and unnecessary, and we’d have to
                convert back to SGML anyway.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">Not to mention that the client was fine with SGML, too. The issue was
                not SGML, the issue was an aging system that couldn’t keep up.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">My employer was in the process of merging with another consultancy,
                however, and the players all needed to score. They both liked Documentum and were
                partners with them, so there were political advantages to using it. For the
                business, that is; never mind the client. So they decided they need XML because XML
                is modern and new and hip, and it will brush your teeth in the evening and wake you
                up with coffee the next day. And besides, Documentum wouldn’t do SGML.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">The process dragged on and on, and I was eventually pulled from the
                project. I left the company not too long after. The thing they ended up building was
                an absolute disaster that was eventually settled in court while the client bought a
                competitor’s product instead.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Sometimes Word Is What You Want</title>
            <para dir="ltr">Most legal publisher use Word in one way or another. I worked with one
                that published Precedents document templates for lawyers in Word format, in spite of
                the Word files actually being produced in XML, added some intricate and very clever
                tagging, and then converted to Word. As an XML geek, I was dead against this, of
                course. Word seemed like an unnecessary extra layer.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">But when I put aside my pride and supposed XML competence, and really
                started thinking about the process, I realised how wrong I was: the end users are
                non-technical lawyers and it would be a lot more complex (technically and
                politically) to get them to use an XML tool, regardless of all the cool things we
                could do the make life easier for them.</para>
            <para dir="ltr">Sometimes MS Word is what you really want.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Things We Found in the Ashes</title>
        <!--This is sort of like conclusions-->
        <para>It goes without saying. First rule of thumb: be pragmatic. Not only do you have to make
            a living. Sometimes you need to swallow your pride and go for the poor solution. Trying
            to push the purist solution you know would work, might make you sleep better. But at the
            end of the day, do whatever it takes to make things work... if if you know deep down it
            is stupid.</para>
        <para dir="ltr">Drink a lot of coffee... or beer. Companies do have organisational charts
            and official guidelines. But it is the unwritten rules in the workplace and the personal
            connections that will tell you so much more. You gain valuable knowledge and better
            grasp any political sensitivities by listening to coworkers in an informal
            context.</para>
        <para dir="ltr">Don't ever engage in religious discussions. When <quote>forces</quote> at
            your customer's are convinced that their technology is the one to use, <emphasis>use
                it</emphasis>. You can bring all the arguments you want to the table. Objective
            criteria won't be sufficient to convert the religious inspired.</para>
        <para dir="ltr">Choose your battles, even if you risk frustration over your work.</para>
        <para dir="ltr">But do engage in discussions about licenses. Too many companies have an open
            source software policy because they think it is the same as <quote>free
            software</quote>.</para>
        <para dir="ltr">Valuable time is lost in projects working around restrictions in basic
            freeware. For a small fee one can often buy a lot of robustness, functionality,
            performance, etc. But also, someone has to develop and maintain the tools you use. One
            should always consider the long term validity of what you build and bring.</para>
        <para dir="ltr">For the long-term benefit of your customer, this is a battle worth
            fighting.</para>
        <para dir="ltr">Don't bargain on your price. Failure is inherent if you bridge a large gap
            in price discussions.</para>
        <para dir="ltr">You sell value, not hours. If the customer thinks you're valued lower than
            you do yourself and you agree on a compromise higher than theirs and lower than yours,
            you are about to be hired for the wrong job. They will think they are paying you too
            much for what you do, and you will be frustrated because you know they make you do
            things for less than they should be paying.</para>
        <para dir="ltr">Get your responsibilities straight from the start.</para>
        <para dir="ltr">Customers often don't realize what exactly they are hiring you for. A quick
            development task at a fair price, will most likely lead to taking over an architect role
            for a longer time for the wrong price. Try to discover early what the roles are, and
            guide your boundaries</para>
        <para dir="ltr">Organize yourself to be able to get out quickly by offering a solid long
            term self sustainability.</para>
        <para dir="ltr">Develop and document whatever you do as if you won't come back tomorrow. You
            don't want these projects to continue to haunt you for the rest of your life.</para>
        <para dir="ltr">And if they do haunt you... you've made sure you can get back in with a
            smile</para>
        <para dir="ltr">Accept failure gracefully. You can only do the best you can do. Some
            projects simply fail. Because of you or despite of you.</para>
        <para dir="ltr">We are all very proud people. Yet, there is no shame in admitting that one
            project or another has failed... and that you might have played a role in that failure.
            Maybe you did not push enough for a change, maybe you did not pay attention. Maybe you
            (shudder) were wrong.</para>
    </section>
</article>
